Guide to the John C. Gore, Sr. family papers M1847
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
John C. Gore, Sr. family papers
1833-1952
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Gore, John C., Sr.
Gore family
M1847
1.5 Linear Feet (4 boxes)
Papers of John C. Gore and family, principally concerned with a property dispute in Rancho Pescadero (now Pebble Beach), California.
Access to Collection
Open for research. Note that material must be requested at least 36 hours in advance of intended use.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased, 2011. Accession 2011-140.
Scope and Contents
The Gore family lived on the 4400-acre Rancho Pescadero, California, (now Pebble Beach) and was involved in a land dispute with David Jacks and later the Pacific Improvement Company over this property. John C. Gore, Sr. had purchased the Rancho in 1852 from the widow of John Frederick Romie, who died while mining in Placerville in 1850. Romie had bought the land from Maria Madariaga four years prior. However, in 1860 Madariaga sold the land once more to investor David Jacks, who already owned the adjoining Rancho Aguajito. He also married the daughter of John Frederick and Maria Romie. Litigation over the two deeds to the former Mexican land grant began in 1860, made more complicated by Jacks' sale of the land to the Pacific Improvement Company in 1880. Included is a 150-page manuscript vellum-bound diary/journal, numerous manuscript letters, and notes dealing specifically with the dispute and subsequent legal proceedings between the Gore family and David Jacks, contemporary copies of pleadings and exhibits in the case, and a large quantity of other material related to the Monterey area, Rancho Pescadero, as well as family correspondence and documents.
Related Materials
Stanford Special collections also holds the David Jacks papers, 1845-1905 (M0068): https://searchworks.stanford.edu/view/4082762 as well as several collections on the Pacific Improvement Company, including JL001 (https://searchworks.stanford.edu/view/4082959) and JL017 (https://searchworks.stanford.edu/view/4082958).
Pebble Beach (Calif.); Monterey County (Calif.) -- History.; Law -- California -- Monterey County -- History.; Rancho Pescadero (Barreto); Gore, John C., Sr.; Gore family; Jacks, David, 1822-1909; Pacific Improvement Company
- Legal papers
  - Sworn Statement of Assistant Librarian of Congressional Library re David Jacks Naturalization Records (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Jacks v Gore: Affidavit, February 16, 1864, of John Gore (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Tompkins Estate (Copy of Will), November 24, 1872 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Gore v Jacks: Petition for Allowance of Appeal, June 1904 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Bond/Edward Tompkins to Marinus Price (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Indenture/Elizabeth Jane, the wife of James Henry Thomas Vaughan Hughes, Spectember 6, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Deed to J.J. O'Farrell, Alameda County, January 10, 1896 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Supreme Court re Appeal of Circuit Court, October term, 1904. Gore and Howard v. United States, David Jacks, and Pacific Improvement Conpany, Defendants and Appellees (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Copy of Statement of Facts in Pescadero Case, as made by John C. Gore Sr. (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - John C Gore Jr, and Hamilton Gay Howard, Complaints v the United States, David Jacks, and Pacific Improvement Company, Defendants. Case # 13,549: petition for Writ of Mandate, February 16, 1904 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Index to Exhibits of Bill of Complaints (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - John C Gore Jr, and Hamilton Gay Howard, Complaints v the United States, David Jacks, and Pacific Improvement Company, Defendants. Case # 13,549: petition for Writ of Mandate, February 16, 1904: Dismissal and Final Decree (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Taxes for Ten Years, showing the Valuation of the Rancho Pescadero and the number of Acres it contained from 1853 to 1863 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - B.F. Ankenys Receipts, 1860 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Certification of Power of Attorney, John C Gore to Frederick Seymour, 1903 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - No. 39 Letters Supplementary to the Trade with Tompkins, November 29, 1860 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Mortgage, Edward Thompkins to M Pierce, copy, 1855 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - The United States,Complaintant,v David Jacks, and Pacific Improvement Company, Defendants. Original Bill of Complaint (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Gore to Seymour: Correspondence, copy, September 7, 1860 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Copy of Frederick Seymour's Discharge for Debt, 1862, Exhibit 75-A (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Estate of Mrs Vaughan Hughes, deceased, re W. Arthur Bennett Hale Gore's Legacy, 1911 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - John C Gore Jr, and Hamilton Gay Howard, Complaints v the United States, David Jacks, and Pacific Improvement Company, Defendants. Case # 13,549: Petition for Writ or Mandate [?] (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - John C Gore Jr, and Hamilton Gay Howard, Complaints v the United States, David Jacks, and Pacific Improvement Company, Defendants. Case # 13,549: Hearing on Demurrers [?] (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - American Bonding Company of Baltimore: Authorization of Business Charter, February 1904 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Certificate of Title, Matilda Hale Gore, # 4117/Title 5842-77, Alameda County, 1896 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Warranty Deed, William Barrett to John C. Gore, August 1860 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Documents relating to taxes on Rancho Pescadero (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Documents regarding payment of 1862 Rancho Pescadero property taxes (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - John C. Gore: Copy of original affadavit, March 20, 1861 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Miscellaneous legal documents (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Legal exhibits
  - Exhibits 1-6, 10-16 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Exhibits 17-21, 23-29 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Exhibits 30-37 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Jacks v Gore: Exhibit 38 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Jacks v Gore: Exhibit 39 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Exhibits 40-47 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Exhibits 48-62 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Exhibits 63-71, 73, 74, 86 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Jacks v Gore: Exhibits 75-83 (Box 1, Folders 7-15)
  - Jacks v Gore: Exhibit 85, March 27, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence
  - Miscellaneous correspondence (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Frederick Seymour, Correspondence (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - John C. Gore Correspondence (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - John C. Gore and Fredrick Seymour: Correspondence/Documents (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Arthur B. Gore
  - A.B. Gore Hamilton college diplomas, 1915 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Grant Deed to Arthur Gore, Gas and Water Easement, Pacific Grove property, some family information, June 16, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Arthur B. Gore and Elizabeth S. Gore, Affidavit, February 9, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Arthur Bennett Gore's handwritten Autobiography, June 25, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Poetry (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Poems (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Arthur Gore Poetry (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Dr. Arthur Gore- published poetry (newspaper clippings) (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Dr. Arthur Gore- manuscript drafts, poetry (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Dr. Arthur Gore- typescript drafts, poetry (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Dr. Arthur Gore- typescript drafts, poetry (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Dr. Arthur Gore fan mail (Box 2, Folder 37)
- Family
  - Photograph Negatives (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - John Gore family information (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Family papers (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Jack's School Work, 1927; and Jack's Senior Sweater Numbers, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Photograph negatives, Jack and Ruby (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - John B. Gore diplomas etc., 1930s-1940s (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Miscellaneous ephemera and negatives (Jacks Wedding Pictures) (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Other material
  - Ephemera and correspondence, oversize (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - John C. Gore National Academy of Design membership, 1833 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Diary of John C Gore Sr. [vellum bound] (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Diary 2 of John C. Gore Sr., 1862-1864 (Box 4)
  - Masonic Papers, 1883 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Clippings- obituaries (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Clippings - American presidents feature etc. (Box 2, Folder 32)